[
    {
        "question": "How did the environment of the Mesopotamian region change over time?",
        "a": "The climate became more humid.",
        "b": "The diversity of wildlife increased.",
        "c": "Precipitation levels decreased.",
        "d": "Temperature fluctuations became more extreme.",
        "e": "Soil fertility increased.",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "The Mesopotamians sourced their water from the",
        "a": "Persian Gulf",
        "b": "Mediterranean Sea",
        "c": "Tigris and Euphrates Rivers",
        "d": "Nile River",
        "e": "Indus River",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which innovations are MOST associated with the Sumerians?",
        "a": "animal domestication and sculpture",
        "b": "metalworking and roads",
        "c": "calendars and mapmaking",
        "d": "writing and planned cities",
        "e": "irrigation systems and textiles",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "All of the following civilizations developed in Mesopotamia EXCEPT",
        "a": "Persian",
        "b": "Assyrian",
        "c": "Babylonian",
        "d": "Akkadian",
        "e": "Anatolian",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "When did the Akkadian Empire rise to power?",
        "a": "the Mesolithic Age",
        "b": "the Early Holocene",
        "c": "the Middle Holocene",
        "d": "the Paleolithic Age",
        "e": "the Late Holocene",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which environmental condition caused the collapse of the Old Kingdom in Egypt?",
        "a": "earthquakes",
        "b": "floods",
        "c": "droughts",
        "d": "volcanic eruptions",
        "e": "storms",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "How did the ancient Egyptians manipulate the environment?",
        "a": "by creating new natural fertilizers",
        "b": "by creating artificial lakes and reservoirs",
        "c": "by developing irrigation systems",
        "d": "by building terraces on hillsides for farming",
        "e": "by planting trees to create windbreaks",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "Scholars believe the ancient Egyptians developed an early model of",
        "a": "waste management",
        "b": "afforestation",
        "c": "sustainable farming",
        "d": "eco-friendly urban planning",
        "e": "desert reclamation",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "In which present-day country did the Indus Civilization develop?",
        "a": "Nepal",
        "b": "Iran",
        "c": "Pakistan",
        "d": "Afghanistan",
        "e": "India",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which time period witnessed urbanization and population growth in the Indus Civilization?",
        "a": "the Early Harappan phase",
        "b": "the Late Harappan Phase",
        "c": "the Pre-Harappan phase",
        "d": "the Mature Harappan phase",
        "e": "the Middle Harappan phase",
        "correct_answer": "a"
    },
    {
        "question": "How did the Indus Civilization change during the Late Harappan phase?",
        "a": "Religious practices became more centralized.",
        "b": "Agricultural productivity declined.",
        "c": "Trade networks expanded to distant regions.",
        "d": "Increased urbanization caused environmental degradation.",
        "e": "People settled in smaller villages.",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where did the Inca Empire develop?",
        "a": "Mesoamerica",
        "b": "the Caribbean",
        "c": "the Yucatán Peninsula",
        "d": "the Andes Mountains",
        "e": "the Gulf Coast",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following civilizations developed in the same region as the Maya and the Aztec?",
        "a": "the Nazca",
        "b": "the Olmec",
        "c": "the Cahokia",
        "d": "the Chavín",
        "e": "the Tiwanaku",
        "correct_answer": "b"
    },
    {
        "question": "The environment of the Americas PRIMARILY features",
        "a": "extensive deserts and rolling plains",
        "b": "tropical rainforests and arid plateaus",
        "c": "coastal wetlands and grasslands",
        "d": "high mountains and extensive vegetation",
        "e": "steppes and tundra",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "How was the environment similar in both the Americas and the Eastern Hemisphere during the Holocene?",
        "a": "They saw rapidly rising sea levels.",
        "b": "They had regions of active volcanic activity.",
        "c": "They experienced the formation of large freshwater lakes.",
        "d": "They experienced periods of significant glaciation.",
        "e": "They had fluctuating climatic conditions.",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Where was Alexander the Great born?",
        "a": "Sparta",
        "b": "Thebes",
        "c": "Athens",
        "d": "Corinth",
        "e": "Macedonia",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which common language did Alexander the Great establish among conquered territories?",
        "a": "Greek",
        "b": "Persian",
        "c": "Aramaic",
        "d": "Latin",
        "e": "Egyptian",
        "correct_answer": "a"
    },
    {
        "question": "Around which year was the peak of the Roman empire?",
        "a": "112 CE",
        "b": "120 CE",
        "c": "128 CE",
        "d": "117 CE",
        "e": "132 CE",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which empire inherited Alexander’s conquered land?",
        "a": "Maurya Empire",
        "b": "Roman Empire",
        "c": "Persian Empire",
        "d": "Ottoman Empire",
        "e": "Byzantine Empire",
        "correct_answer": "b"
    },
    {
        "question": "What climatic conditions prevailed in the Mediterranean from 800 to 500 BCE?",
        "a": "predictable rainfall",
        "b": "extreme drought",
        "c": "frequent storms",
        "d": "severe cold spells",
        "e": "intense heatwaves",
        "correct_answer": "a"
    },
    {
        "question": "The growing power of Greek city-states in the Roman Empire could be linked to",
        "a": "politically weak surrounding territories",
        "b": "increased trade and exploration",
        "c": "advances in military technology",
        "d": "favorable farming conditions",
        "e": "cultural isolation from surrounding territories",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which Chinese dynasty ruled from 618 to 907 CE?",
        "a": "Tang Dynasty",
        "b": "Song Dynasty",
        "c": "Qing Dynasty",
        "d": "Han Dynasty",
        "e": "Sui Dynasty",
        "correct_answer": "a"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which era lasted until about 1450 or 1500?",
        "a": "Enlightenment",
        "b": "Middle Ages",
        "c": "Renaissance",
        "d": "Industrial Revolution",
        "e": "Baroque",
        "correct_answer": "b"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which era ran from 1300 to 1600?",
        "a": "Middle Ages",
        "b": "Enlightenment",
        "c": "Baroque",
        "d": "Industrial Revolution",
        "e": "Renaissance",
        "correct_answer": "e"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why are the early Middle Ages known as the Dark Ages?",
        "a": "There was a substantial decline in religious beliefs and practices.",
        "b": "They were defined by a decline in culture and technology.",
        "c": "Frequent natural disasters led to famine and political unrest.",
        "d": "Volcanic eruptions lowered available sunlight.",
        "e": "Sun cycles caused unnaturally persistent cloud cover.",
        "correct_answer": "b"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which year did Michael McCormick describe as the 'worst year to be alive?'",
        "a": "562 CE",
        "b": "523 CE",
        "c": "536 CE",
        "d": "563 CE",
        "e": "570 CE",
        "correct_answer": "c"
    },
    {
        "question": "Chinese human records date from the",
        "a": "Zhou Dynasty",
        "b": "Yuan Dynasty",
        "c": "Jin Dynasty",
        "d": "Shang Dynasty",
        "e": "Song Dynasty",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "What climatic conditions coincided with population growth in China?",
        "a": "stable temperatures",
        "b": "unpredictable wind patterns",
        "c": "frequent monsoons",
        "d": "warming periods",
        "e": "cooler temperatures",
        "correct_answer": "d"
    },
    {
        "question": "During which dynasty was the mandate of heaven established?",
        "a": "Zhou Dynasty",
        "b": "Yuan Dynasty",
        "c": "Jin Dynasty",
        "d": "Shang Dynasty",
        "e": "Song Dynasty",
        "correct_answer": "a"
    },
    {
        "question": "The mandate of heaven held that",
        "a": "all roles are predestined",
        "b": "external conditions validated rulers’ authority",
        "c": "rule can only be inherited",
        "d": "spiritual practice leads to higher social status",
        "e": "a ruler’s success depends on military conquests",
        "correct_answer": "b"
    }
]
